Chris Coenen Collection on General Tom Thumb MS254
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- Stereographs, 1858 -- 1892; MS254.001268
  This series contains stereographs related to Tom Thumb. Stereographs are two nearly identical photographs displayed side by side and meant to be viewed with a stereoscope. When viewed through the stereoscope, the stereographs appear three-dimensional. Subjects of these stereographs include Tom Thumb, the Barnum Museum, Lavinia Warren, Count Primo Magri, Ernesto Magri, Commodore Nutt, and Tom Thumb and Lavinia Warren's wedding.
  - Tom as lady killer,; Cremer, Philadelphia, 1858; MS254.001269 (Box 11)
    May be a copy of an LSC stereo
  - Toasting Tom Thumb as Highlander, LSC, London, 1858; MS254.001270 (Box 11)
    Toasting Tom
  - Tom as Highlander with PT Barnum, colored, LSC,London, 1858; MS254.001271 (Box 11)
    A hand colored version of 421
  - Banquet with Tom Thumb as Highlander, LSC, London, 1858; MS254.001272 (Box 11)
    Banquet with toast
  - Tom as Highlander with ladies, LSC, London, 1858; MS254.001273 (Box 11)
    Tom Thumb impressing the ladies
  - Tom Thumb as little girl, LSC, London, 1858; MS254.001274 (Box 11)
    Tom in one of his characters
  - Tom Thumb wooing lady, 1858; MS254.001275 (Box 11)
    Tom on bended knee
  - Tom Thumb on ladies lap, 1858; MS254.001276 (Box 11)
    Tom sitting on a lap
  - Tom Thumb kissing ladies hand, 1858; MS254.001277 (Box 11)
    Tom had a reputation of kissing thousands of women
  - Tom Thumb's Lifeguard, 1858; MS254.001278 (Box 11)
    Apparently, Tom Thumb was assigned his own personal lifeguard by the Queen
  - Copy stereo of Tom Thumb in character fighting a flamingo, LSC, London, 1858; MS254.001279 (Box 11)
    Copy of Tom posing as statuary
  - Crystal Palace, London, 1860; MS254.001280 (Box 11)
    Tom Thumb performed at the Crystal Palace; the first one burned and was replaced by one in Bromley
  - Barnum's Museum, NY, 1859; hand colored; Anthony, MS254.001281 (Box 11)
    "Broadway From Corner of Murray St., Looking South"
  - Barnum's Museum, NY, 1859; Anthony, MS254.001282 (Box 11)
    Un-tinted version of 435
  - Barnum's Museum on Broadway, later copy, 1859; MS254.001283 (Box 11)
    Later copy of an earlier view of the Museum
  - View of Broadway, looking North from Barnum's Museum; Anthony, NY, 1860; MS254.001284 (Box 11)
    Looking Norh rom Barnum's Museum; City Hall Park on right
  - Broadway looking North from Barnum's Museum, 1860; MS254.001285 (Box 11)
    City Hall Park on right
  - Up Broadway from Barnum's Museum, 1860; MS254.001286 (Box 11)
  - Park Row from Barnum's Museum- The City Hall Park on the left, Anthony, NY, 1860; MS254.001287 (Box 11)
    Park Row
  - Ruins of Barnum Museum looking up Broadway, 1865; MS254.001288 (Box 11)
    Ruins of the Museum in the foreground
  - Looking up Broadway from the corner of Fulton St.showing the ruins of Barnum's Museum, Anthony NY, 1865; MS254.001289 (Box 11)
    Ruins in the foreground
  - Broadway from corner of Murray St., looking South;Barnum's Museum; Anthony, NY, 1859; MS254.001290 (Box 11)
    Barnum's Museum in the background
  - Broadway From Barnum's Museum, Looking North;Anthony, NY, 1859; MS254.001291 (Box 11)
    Looking North from the Museum
  - Broadway from Barnum's Museum; Anthony, NY, 1859; MS254.001292 (Box 11)
    Busy Broadway
  - Barnum's second Museum, 1867; MS254.001293 (Box 11)
    After the fire of 1865 destroyed the original Museum, Barnum built a second up Broadway
  - Burned second Museum, 1868; MS254.001294 (Box 11)
    Barnum's second museum burned on March 3, 1868
  - Burned second Museum; later copy, 1868; MS254.001295 (Box 11)
    Showing the ice-covered remains
  - Ruins of second Museum, 1868; MS254.001296 (Box 11)
    Another view of the burned Museum
  - Barnum's Museum after the fire of 1868, MS254.001297 (Box 11)
    Ice covered ruins
  - Barnum's Roman Hippodrome; in New York City; Moulton of Salem, Ma., 1870; MS254.001298 (Box 11)
    Another Barnum venture in NY
  - Tom Thumb and his carriage, LSC, London, 1859; MS254.001299 (Box 11)
    Barnum had a miniature carriage built during their first trip to England in the 1840's
  - Tom Thumb riding atop his carriage, LSC, London, 1859; MS254.001300 (Box 11)
    Carriage with Tom next to coachman
  - Tom and coach with man; LSC, London, 1859; MS254.001301 (Box 11)
    Looking at Tom in the coach
  - Tom in Bridgeport, Ct. with friends admiring his coach; Whitney, Norwalk, CT.; Digital copy only, 1860; MS254.001302 (Box 11)
    Taken in Bridgeport area which was Charles Stratton's home town; original in the Coenen Collection
  - Ernesto, Lavinia and Primo Magri posed by a carriage; Kilburn, 1889; MS254.001303 (Box 11)
    This is probably not the original carriage from the 1840's; not sure if the Queen ever gave Tom Thumb a carriage
  - Tom Thumb, Charles Stratton, with man, perhaps tutor; from England, 1858; MS254.001304 (Box 11)
    Tom Thumb posed with a man; might be a tutor or translator hired by Barnum; originally from England
  - Commodore Nutt, Lavinia Warren, W. B Harrison, Charles Stratton, 1863; MS254.001305 (Box 11)
    WB Harrison was an actor at Barnum's American Museum and friend of the Strattons; introduced Lavinia on stage in 1863
  - Staged marriage, Brady, NY; tax stamp, 1863; MS254.001306 (Box 11)
    Part of the series done by Brady shortly before the wedding
  - Staged marriage by Brady II, 1863; MS254.001307 (Box 11)
    Part of the marriage series (Lilliputian Series)
  - Staged marriage by Brady III, 1863; MS254.001308 (Box 11)
  - Staged marriage by Brady, IV, 1863; MS254.001309 (Box 11)
  - The Fairy Wedding Party; by Brady, 1863; MS254.001310 (Box 11)
    The wedding group
  - The Fairy Wedding Party; by Brady; hand colored; same as 464; tax stamp, 1863; MS254.001311 (Box 11)
    Colored version
  - Tom Thumb's Wedding; later copy, Keystone, 1863; MS254.001312 (Box 11)
    Keystone copy of the wedding party
  - Commodore Nutt and Minnie Warren, 1863; MS254.001313 (Box 11)
    Re-used stereo of Nutt and Warren
  - Minnie Warren on posing chair, 1863; MS254.001314 (Box 11)
    The Fairy Bridesmaid
  - Minnie Warren standing, 1863; MS254.001315 (Box 11)
    Fairy Bridesmaid
  - Commodore Nutt standing, 1865; MS254.001316 (Box 11)
    A little later version of Nutt
  - Lavinia Warren and hoax baby; tax stamp; hand colored, 1864; MS254.001317 (Box 11)
    Stereo copy of the baby cdv
  - The Fairy Bride and Bridegroom, 1863; MS254.001318 (Box 11)
    Tom sitting in the chair
  - Tom and Lavinia standing as Groom and Bride, 1863; MS254.001319 (Box 11)
    Stading version
  - New York Street scene, poster of Tom Thumb on the fence; newsboys?, 1863; MS254.001320 (Box 11)
    Perhaps newsboys posed in New York in front of biilboards
  - Children's Tom Thumb Wedding, 1863; MS254.001321 (Box 11)
    Children's copy of wedding
  - Lindencroft, Barnum's home in Bridgeport, Ct., 1860; MS254.001322 (Box 11)
    Lindencroft was on of several homes Barnum had in Bridgeport; this is where Charles Stratton proposed to Lavinia Warren
  - Parlor at Lindencroft with 1865 tax stamp, MS254.001323 (Box 11)
    According to the story, this is where Charles Stratton proposed to Lavinia Warren in Jan. 1863
  - Broadway, looking South from the balcony of the Metropolitan Hotel, 1859; MS254.001324 (Box 11)
    The wedding reception was held at the Metropolitan Hotel; later that night a crowd and band gathered to serenade the couple and Tom came out on a balcony to thank them
  - "Tom Thumb's Carriage"; the nutshell carriage was originally built for Commodore Nutt; G.W.C. Carter, photographer; digital copy only, 1875; MS254.001325 (Box 11)
    Tom Thumb's coach in winter at an unknown location; original in the Coenen Collection
  - Antietam, Colossal Granite Statue, Westerly,R.I.;; little people out front; Schofield, Westerly; digital copy only, 1875; MS254.001326 (Box 11)
    From L. to R.: Sylvester Bleeker, mgr.; Charles Stratton; Lavinia Warren;Commodore Nutt; Minnie Warren; Mrs. Bleeker; unknown man; original in Coenen Collection
  - Tom Thumb's gravesite, Bridgeport, Ct.; Wilson, Bridgeport; digital copy only, 1885; MS254.001327 (Box 11)
    Tom is buried in the Stratton family plot in Mountain Grove Cemetery across from P.T. Barnum; the original statue was vandalized and eventuall a lower pedestal with another statue was placed on top; he has a small marker out front and next to him is Lavinia; her marker says "His Wife"; original in the Coenen Collection
  - Grace Church and Stewart's Store, 1863; MS254.001328 (Box 11)
    Tom Thumb's Wedding took place at Grace Church; Stewart's was one of the first department stores
  - Grace Church, Broadway, 1863; MS254.001329 (Box 11)
    Another view of Grace Church
  - Grace Church in the 1890's; Kilburn, 1892; MS254.001330 (Box 11)
    Later view of Grace Church
  - Trinity Church, NYC, 1860; MS254.001331 (Box 11)
    Lavinia married Primo Magri in Trinity Church in 1885
  - Trinity Church, close, 1884; MS254.001332 (Box 11)
    Close view of Trinity Church
  - Overview of Middleboro, Mass.; Lavinia's home town, 1865; MS254.001333 (Box 11)
    This is Middleboro around the time Lavinia Warren married General Tom Thumb; her family lived at the North end of the town
  - Old Pierce Academy, Middleboro, Mass., 1865; MS254.001334 (Box 11)
    In her later years, Lavinia would sometimes perform here
  - Center St.; J.W. Pierce Store and Ryder House, Middleboro, Mass., 1865; MS254.001335 (Box 11)
    Lavinia's home town
  - Charles Stratton and Lavinia Warren's House, Middleboro, Mass.; Tom Thumb out front, 1880; MS254.001336 (Box 11)
    Tom is posed with a dog outside the house. The home was built Ca. 1870 while they were on their world tour.; the dimensions were altered to suit their needs- lower window frames, shorter stair treads, etc.; home is owned privately in Middleboro across from the Bump homestead
  - Stratton-Warren House in Middleboro; Tom Thumb out front with horses, 1880; MS254.001337 (Box 11)
    Tom is posed with two horses; women are posibly Lavinia's sisters.
  - St. Paul's from the corner of Broadway and Fulton St., 1860; MS254.001338 (Box 11)
    St. Paul's was across the street from Barnum's American Museum
  - The Broadway Bridge, including St. Paul's Church and the Astor House, 1860; MS254.001339 (Box 11)
    This would have been in front of Barnum's Museum; not sure if it is before or after the fire of 1865
  - The Boradway Bridge; variation of 493, 1860; MS254.001340 (Box 11)
  - The Grand Central Depot, 42d St and 4th Ave,, NYC, 1871; MS254.001341 (Box 11)
    Charles and Lavinia would use this depot to get back to Bridgeport
  - Castle Garden, NYC, 1870; MS254.001342 (Box 11)
    PT Barnum introduced Jenny Lind in her first American concert at Castle Garden
  - Castle Garden, NYC II, 1870; MS254.001343 (Box 11)
  - Castle Garden and Liberty Statue, NYC; Underwood, 1890; MS254.001344 (Box 11)
    Later view of Castle Garden after Statue of Liberty was erected
  - The Park National Bank and Herald Building, NYC, 1860; MS254.001345 (Box 11)
    Barnum had a close relationship with several newspapers who published articles about Barnum and his endeavors
  - Tribune Building, 1860; MS254.001346 (Box 11)
  - Boston Museum; Moses Kimball, 1860; MS254.001347 (Box 11)
    Moses Kimball was a friend and sometimes colleague of PT Barnum; they shared ownership of the Feejee Mermaid; Kimball ran the Boston Museum
  - Parker House, Boston, 1860; MS254.001348 (Box 11)
    Lavinia sometimes stayed at the Parker House
  - St. Nicholas Hotel, New York City, 1860; MS254.001349 (Box 11)
    Used by the "little people"
  - St. Nicholas Hotel, NYC, 1875; MS254.001350 (Box 11)
  - Broadway from Houston St., Looking North. Winter; Museum of Anatomy; Photographic establishment, 1870; MS254.001351 (Box 11)
    Museum of Anatomy; solar printers on the roof
  - Grand Opera House, NYC, 1870; MS254.001352 (Box 11)
    Grand Opera House
  - Booth's Theater, NYC, 1870; MS254.001353 (Box 11)
    Booth's Theater
  - Academy of Music, NYC, 1870; MS254.001354 (Box 9)
    Academy of Music, Fourteenth St.
  - Academy of Music, Fourteenth St., NYC, 1870; MS254.001355 (Box 9)
  - Astor House, NYC; near Barnum's Museum, 1865; MS254.001356 (Box 9)
    Astor House, across from the American Museum
  - Fifth Avenue Hotel, NYC, 1874; MS254.001357 (Box 9)
    Fifth Avenue Hotel
  - Fifth Avenue Hotel, NYC, 1870; MS254.001358 (Box 9)
  - Masonic Temole, Philadelphia, 1873; MS254.001359 (Box 9)
    Masonic Temple
  - Cooper Institute, NYC; became Cooper Union, 1870; MS254.001360 (Box 9)
    Peter Cooper invented a small steam engine he called "Tom Thumb"
  - Masonic Temple, NYC, 1875; MS254.001361 (Box 9)
    Masonic Temple, NYC
  - PT Barnum and Charles Stratton;LSC, London, 1858; MS254.001362 (Box 9)
    Tom Thumb accompanied Barnum on his tour of Europe after his he went bankrupt from the Jerome Clock fiasco
  - Tom Thumb in his Characters; LSC, London, 1858; MS254.001363 (Box 9)
    Tom in one of his personalities
  - Tom Thumb as Highlander impressing the ladies; LSC, London, 1858; MS254.001364 (Box 9)
    Tom Thumb as Highlander
  - Lavinia in two baby portraits mounted as a stereo, 1864; MS254.001365 (Box 9)
    Man on the left could be Barnum
  - General Tom Thumb's Wife & Child; Anthony, NY, 1864; MS254.001366 (Box 9)
    One of the baby portraits as a stereo
  - Mock Tom Thumb Wedding, Moulton, Salem, Ma., 1865; MS254.001367 (Box 9)
    Due to the popularity of the little people, mock Tom Thumb weddings using children popped-up; these children's entertaiments persisted into the 1950's
  - "Not Tom Thumb and his Wife", 1870; MS254.001368 (Box 9)
    Cute but labled on back as "29. Not Tom Thumb and His Wife"
  - Mock Tom Thumb Wedding; Smith, Austin, Minn., 1870; MS254.001369 (Box 9)
    Cute children
  - Mrs. Tom Thumb and carriage presented to her by Queen Victoria stereograph, circa 1890; circa 1980; MS254.001464 (Box 11)